

4225 Pendleton Dr. Apt. 7104 Bryan, TX, 77802, USA

□ (281)-825-9621 | Image: Ima

Summary.

As a computational biologist, I enjoy the puzzle-like nature of coding genetics and genomics problems, specifically bringing this approach to the evolution of genomic content and sex chromosomes. Detail-oriented planning, project management, experimental design, and clear communication are important to my critical thinking and problem solving strategies for research. I am pursuing a Ph.D. in Genetics and Genomics at Texas A&M University with an expected graduation date of Spring 2023, and I am interested in career paths in industry intersecting genetics, genomics, data science, and molecular biology.

Expertise

Genomics: SRA, Trimmomatic, bwa, samtools, bamtools, GATK, PLINK, BUSCO, rrBLUP, GEMMA

Genetics: Genome structure evolution, Sex chromosome evolution, Morphometrics, Genomic analysis, Genome assembly

Molecular Biology: Primer optimization, gDNA/DNA extraction, RNA extraction, PCR, qPCR, Gel visualization/imaging

Programming: R, Linux/Unix, Git, tidyverse, conda, Python (Beginner), LaTeX, HTML/CSS, Shiny

Data Science: Large dataset management (>20Gb), Bayesian statistics, Phylogenetics, Simulations, Data Visualization (ggplot2), Software

Development

Soft Skills: Project management, Public Speaking, Leadership, Multi-disciplinary Collaboration, Adaptive problem solving

Education

Ph.D. in Genetics and Genomics (Graduate Business Certificate)

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M UNIVERSITY | ADVISOR: HEATH BLACKMON

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

• Dissertation: The Rise and Fall of DNA Sequences Among Sequence Classes and Genomic Compartments

B.S. in Forensic and Investigative Science (Minor: Genetics)

Texas A&M University | Advisor: Aaron M. Tarone

• Thesis: Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology

College Station, Texas

Aug. 2014 - May 2018

Experience_

PetDx San Diego, California

BIOINFORMATICS INTERN | BIOINFORMATICS AND DATA SCIENCE TEAM

June 2022 - Aug. 2022

- Leveraged high-complexity data set to predict canine cancer types
- Used machine learning (Random Forest) approaches to train and evaluate different models
- Performed extensive data evaluation to curate sample metrics, obtain balanced training and testing sets and identify meaningful model parameters

Bayer Crop Science St. Louis, Missouri

DATA SCIENCE INTERN | GENOMICS DISCOVERY AND APPLICATION TEAM

May 2021 - Aug. 2021

- · Identifying historic data to test for epistasis and designing a follow-up experiment to test for epistasis
- Developing a statistical testing framework to identify interactions between introgressed loci
- Three-month, full-time position exposure in an industry setting
- · Establishing multi-disciplinary connections with teams with expertise in data science, genomics, and precision breeding

Ph.D. Research | Advisor: Dr. Heath Blackmon

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M INTERDISCIPLINARY PROGRAM IN GENETICS AND GENOMICS | TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY

Aug. 2018 - May 2023

- Developing an R package (Lo et al. 2019) to characterize microsatellite evolution and applying this package to characterize microsatellite evolution across 300 million years of insect evolution (Jonika et al. 2020)
- Elucidating the role of centromere type in insect chromosome evolution (Ruckman et al. 2020)
- Designing an automated genomic pipeline and TensorFlow based machine learning application to categorize genomic characteristics for 100s of mammalian species totaling 1000s of TB of genomic data

Post-baccalaureate Research Technician | Advisor: Dr. Aaron M. Tarone

College Station, Texas

TEXAS A&M DEPARTMENT OF ENTOMOLOGY

May 2018 - Aug. 2018

- Completed additional experimentation and formal writing from undergraduate thesis project (Jonika et al. 2020)
- Applied new sex determination methodology and primer optimization to additional applications in forensic entomology (Pimsler et al. 2021) and stem cell research (Pitonak et al. 2022)

Teaching & Mentorship

Teaching Assistant

DEPARTMENT OF BIOLOGY | DEPARTMENT OF BIOCHEMISTRY

- Anatomy and Physiology | Spring 2022 | Texas A&M
- Critical Writing in Biology | Fall 2020, Spring 2021 | Texas A&M
- Introduction to Genetics Laboratory | Spring 2019 | Texas A&M
- Guest Lecture Forensic Genetics | Topic: Genetic Testing | Sep. 2022 | Texas A&M
- Guest Lecture Bioinformatics | Topic: Genetic Privacy | Oct. 2019 | Texas A&M
- Guest Lecture Bioinformatics | Topic: Genetic Privacy | Nov. 2021 | Utah Valley University

Graduate Student Mentor

UNDERGRADUATE RESEARCH ASSISTANTS

- Mentee: Johnathan Lo | Topic: Microsatellite Characterization and Evolution
- Mentee: Abhi Arekere | Topic: Carnivore Chromosome Number Evolution
- Mentee: Ragan Miller, Joseph Ward, Leen Fardoun | Topic: Chrysina Morphometrics
- Mentee: Grace Fischer | Topic: Tribolium Dispersal Patterns

Management & Outreach

Genetics Society of America

EARLY CAREER LEADERSHIP PROGRAM - CAREER DEVELOPMENT SUBCOMMITTEE

Jan. 2020 - Current

- Contribute career development blog pieces for Genes to Genomes blog
- Curate resources contributing to a career development toolkit and early career researcher newsletters
- Organize career development workshops for bimonthly workshop series and TAGC conference

Genetics Graduate Student Association

PRESIDENT | VICE PRESIDENT | GRADUATE STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE | SEMINAR COMMITTEE

May 2019 - Current

- Facilitate monthly graduate student association meetings
- Oversee communication between current graduate students, genetics faculty, and the program executive committee

Coding Workshop Facilitator and Instructor

F: FACILITATOR | T: TAUGHT | *: CO-TAUGHT

Apr. 2019 - Current

- Texas Genetics Society R Workshop, TGS F (150 attendees)
- R Hackday, Texas A&M Department of Biology T* (50 attendees)
- R Workshop, Aggie Veterans Who Code F (15 attendees)

Texas A&M College of Science

OUTREACH COMMITTEE | WOMEN IN SCIENCE AND ENGINEERING

Jan. 2019 - Current

- · Participated in various outreach activities important to the mission of the College of Science and Women in Science and Engineering
- Served on the Women in Science and Engineering outreach committee and organized school STEM nights

Texas Genetics Society

BOARD MEMBER - STUDENT REPRESENTATIVE

Mar. 2020 - Mar. 2022

Organize annual Texas Genetics Society meeting

Awards & Grants

- 2022 **Texas A&M Data Science Ambassador**, Texas A&M University
- 2022 **Research Excellence**, Interdisciplinary Genetics and Genomics Program
- 2021 Outstanding PhD Student Poster Presentation, Texas Genetics Society
- 2020 Outstanding PhD Student Oral Presentation, North America Forensic Entomology Association
- 2019 Genetics Graduate Student Association Travel Grant, Interdisciplinary Genetics and Genomics Program

Selected Publications

M. Pitonak, M. Aceves, P.A. Kumar, G. Dampf, P. Green, A. Tucker, V. Dietz, D. Miranda, S. Letchuman, **M.M. Jonika**, D. Bautista, H. Blackmon, J.N. Dulin. 2022. Effects of Biological Sex Mismatch on Neural ProgenitorCell Transplantation for Spinal Cord Injury in Mice. Nature Communications. In Print.

M.M. Jonika, J.M. Alfieri, T. Sylvester, A.R. Buhrow, H. Blackmon. 2022. Why Not Y Naught. Heredity. 129. 75-78.

S. Ruckman*(Co-first author), M.M. Jonika*(Co-first author), C. Casola, H. Blackmon. 2020. Chromosome Number Evolves at Equal Rates in Holocentric and Monocentric Clades. PLOS Genetics 16(10):e1009076.

M.M. Jonika, C.E. Hjelmen, A.M. Faris, A.S. McGuane A.M. Tarone. 2020. An Evaluation of Differentially Spliced Genes as Markers of Sex for Forensic Entomology. J. of Forensic Science 65(5): 1579-1587

J. Lo, M.M. Jonika, H. Blackmon. 2019. micRocounter: Microsatellite Characterization in Genome Assemblies. G3 9(10): 3101-3104

January 10, 2023 Michelle Jonika · Résumé